<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2015-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Bumbo Baby Seat Review</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/12/23/bumbo.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/12/23/bumbo.html</id>
    <published>2015-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2015-12-23T04:13:12+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Use of the Bumbo is a hotly debated topic. Paediatric physiotherapists passionately advise against
it (see MamaOT's post "&lt;a href="http://mamaot.com/beware-the-baby-bumbo-seat/"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Beware the Bumbo&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,"
for example), while many parents claim it is a God-send. As an occupational therapist,
is there a time when I would recommend the Bumbo seat? Short answer: Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But first, what is a Bumbo seat?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://bumbo.com/products/"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Bumbo&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; floor seat is made of low density 
foam with a colourful coating, making it firm but conforming. It is light-weight, 
and comes in one size only (for this specific product). The tray is optional, detatchable,
and purchased separately. The premise of the Bumbo is that is keeps the baby safely in a
sitting position, before they have developed the ability to sit unsupported. 
It also keeps baby contained, so they can't roll or crawl away unsupervised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bumbo seat lilac and tray" src="/2015/12/23/bumbo/Bumbo2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="caption"&gt;This is an older style Bumbo, before the strap restraints were
introduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bumbo seats (or "Bumbos") are sold in many baby shops and department stores. In 
Australia, a new Bumbo costs about $70, plus the tray. Since they only fit 
for a short period before baby outgrows it, they are also readily available second-hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This video from Bumbo outlines important safety recommendations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/FdB0vRrtLeg" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why do so many developmental specialists advise against the Bumbo?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MamaOT post, linked above, gives a lovely, detailed explanation. Here is the short version:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When a baby is in a Bumbo, he is trapped. Babies need to move around in order to develop their 
sensory systems, gross motor skills, and fine motor skills. A baby that is restricted too often in
a Bumbo, or in any other containment device, may not develop
as expected, and may be delayed in reaching milestones such as rolling, sitting,
crawling and walking.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Therapists (including myself) are bothered by Bumbo marketing that claims baby can "practice"
sitting up. Sitting in a Bumbo does not help a typically developing baby learn to
sit up. Babies learn to sit up by being on the floor.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Bumbo has had a bad wrap for safety issues. Personally, I feel this is probably
a little sensationalised, and not 100% Bumbo's fault. Most of the injuries to children 
seem to have come by the child trying to escape the seat, or moving around too much, and falling
on their heads by tipping the seat over, or by making it fall from a height. Bumbo have added
a seat belt to try to mitigate the risk, but I really don't like the seat belt. I think the
fault here lies in inappropriate use of the Bumbo.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bumbo with Tray" src="/2015/12/23/bumbo/Bumbo1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The tray clips onto the front of the Bumbo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When I have recommended Bumbo and why:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I agree with points outlined in the MamaOT post - when considering &lt;strong&gt;typically 
developing&lt;/strong&gt; children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, not all children are typically developing. The children I work with
have spina bifida or other similar neurological conditions, which means that for some,
learning to sit unsupported is an unrealistic goal. If we put the rest of their development
on hold until they achieve unsupported sitting, they will not reach their developmental 
potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have recommended the Bumbo for children with lower body paralysis over 6 months 
of age, who need to move on to bimanual (two-handed) play to continue development of
their fine motor skills. Many of the children I work with can sit independently by this
age, but need to prop themselves up with one or two arms. This makes play in a sitting
position very difficult and fatiguing. We recommend corner chairs for this same purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bumbo is always used with a tray (or little table) for
their toys, and we discuss implementation with the family so they understand that the
Bumbo is only to be used for up to 30min at a time, while playing. It's not for watching TV,
or sitting for hours while mum does all the housework. It &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; for banging toys together, 
playing 'ta' games, stacking and nesting, with an adult, for up to 30min.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it's back to the floor…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think? Do Bumbos really need to be taken off the market?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Quick Guide to Mobile Shower Commodes</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/12/09/mobileshowercommodes.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/12/09/mobileshowercommodes.html</id>
    <published>2015-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2015-12-09T03:50:55+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Knowing where to start when prescribing a mobile over-toilet shower commode chair can be difficult.
This quick guide to choosing a mobile shower commode outlines the 10 most important questions that I ask myself
or the user, once it has been established that a mobile shower commode
is required. Choosing the best piece of equipment relies on asking the right questions and 
matching the answers to the most useful features. Before I start asking these questions, I've generally already checked 
that the user's bathroom includes enough circulation space and a level-access shower,
and we've had a discussion about how the mobile shower commode will be used (e.g. 
in the shower, over the toilet, or both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prescription of any equipment always needs to consider the user's preferences, safety, and
sound clinical judgement. The questions I use to guide my reasoning probably won't apply 
directly to your situation, but I thought I'd share this to give my fellow therapists some general information
and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Choosing a mobile shower commode chair" src="/2015/12/09/mobileshowercommodes/mobileshowercommodes1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;With so many options it can be hard to make the right choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These first four questions are really to help narrow down the range of products to
consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Can the user self-propel?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A self-propelling mobile shower commode has big wheels at the 
back (or front), and two small castors at the front (or back). Attendant-propelled 
shower commodes just have four small wheels, so the user is unable to move themselves.
Some manufacturers only provide attendant propelled shower chairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tend to prescribe a self-propelling mobile shower commode
where ever the user is physically and cognitively able to push themselves, and the 
circulation space of the environment allows. This gives the user more freedom and
independence, which is also be important in situation where their safety may be compromised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. What are the user's body proportions like?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer this question, I take a general look at the user, and take some measurements (width and weight) if unsure. 
It's important that the shower commode seat fits well and is comfortable. The user's body and feet need to be well supported.
Standard shower commode seats are generally square, except the bariatric sizes, which are wider than their depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Is the user fairly "standard" in their proportions, so they could fit a standard adult size shower commode (440 x 440mm seat)?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are they a child or very small, so they would best fit a paediatric size (330 x 330mm seat)?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are they smaller than a standard adult, but too big for paediatric, so a Junior size would fit best (400 x 400mm seat)?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are they very big, so they would need a bariatric size (550-900mm seat width)?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are they disproportionate? Would minor modifications, or a custom build be required?
A user with very long legs may require a longer seat depth, and longer leg rests. A user with 
short legs and a short torso may require modified or paediatric leg rests, a shorter seat depth, and a lower backrest height.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. How good is the user's postural control?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider what postural support the user requires in other seats. If they have specialised
seating on their wheelchair, it may need to be replicated on the mobile shower commode.
Some mobile shower commodes (such as the Goanna chair or the Seahorse paediatric shower chair)
include a very supportive moulded seat and backrest, which
is great for those who need it, but can be a barrier to thorough washing and limit independence. If the
user has reasonable balance and postural control, I would steer away from this style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minor postural adjustments can be made to many mobile shower commodes, such as adding 
a lap belt, chest strap, lateral positioning wedges, or a higher backrest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Will the user require "tilt in space"?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some users may have medical conditions that require them to be laid back in a hurry. For others,
tilt in space is required so they can achieve a functional position for using the toilet, a safe transfer,
or for hygiene. While tilt in space is often prescribed on wheelchairs for pressure
relief, this is generally not the case for mobile shower commodes due to the much shorter sitting time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mechanics required for tilt in space add weight and bulk to the chair, not to
mention the extra expense. More moving parts also means more that can break, so
I tend to prescribe tilt in space only when absolutely necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next six questions are directed towards narrowing down on specific features or 
accessories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. How will the user transfer into the mobile shower commode?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three main transfer options:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Standing transfer:&lt;/em&gt; If the user is able to sit into the commode seat from a standing position, swing away leg
rests are usually the best option.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Side transfer:&lt;/em&gt; If the user is transferring sideways from one seat to another, the height of the 
shower commode may need to be adjusted to be closer to the height of the other seat. I have had to lower
shower commode seats in the past because the user was transferring from a wheelchair, which was much lower.
This can be a dangerous game though! If you lower it too much the shower commode won't fit over the toilet!
Check your measurements carefully and allow &lt;strong&gt;at least&lt;/strong&gt; an inch (25mm) clearance. For user who are side transferring,
the location and style of the brakes need to be checked so they are accessible and not interferring with the transfer.
Swing-away arm rests are usually required.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hoist transfer:&lt;/em&gt; If the user is hoisted or lifted into the mobile shower commode, tilt in space may be required. 
The shower commode should also have brakes on every wheel (locking castors). 
It's important to talk through the transfer with the user (and carers if applicable) to make sure the 
equipment will be compatible.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. How often and for what duration will the equipment be used?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the mobile shower commode is used only occasionally, or short-term (e.g. post-surgery), perhaps a 
lighter weight, more simple option would be suitable. Some users need their shower commode for up
to 2 hours every day. In this case, it is important to consider comfort features, such as
padded arm rests, and durability of construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. What seat shape will be needed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some shower commode manufacturers (such as K-Care and Otto Bock) sell seats separately to the mobile shower commode
frame. This allows us to match the seat with the needs of the user. It is important 
to understand and consider all the self-care activities the user needs to perform in the mobile
shower commode. Most shower commode seats are made with a ply wood base, foam top, and 
waterproof vinyl covering. They have an aperture (the hole in the middle), which can
vary in shape, size and location. They can be closed front (first two pictured), open front (third
picture), rear or side opening (less common). The can have a 'bite', a cut-out from the side,
to allow more access without compromising the structural integrity of the seat. The 
&lt;a href="https://www.health.qld.gov.au/qscis/html/equipment.asp"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Queensland Spinal Cord Injury Service&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
has some great templates for measuring and drawing custom-designed seats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mobile shower commode seat options" src="/2015/12/09/mobileshowercommodes/mobileshowercommodes2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Three examples of common mobile shower commode seats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main decisions to make:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Machine-made vs Hand-made:&lt;/em&gt; Machine-made seats (pictured above, centre) are generally much cheaper than 
hand-made, however they often have a heat-welded seam along the inside of the aperture and around the sides of the seat,
which can cause problems for fragile skin. Machine-made seats are often less durable as
the seams can split. Hand-made seats are a must for anyone with sensation-loss, as the 
foam is wrapped from the top through the aperture, so the user's bottom isn't resting
on the wooden base. They are also carefully made with no rough edges. I have never prescribed
a machine-made seat, but they may be appropriate for occasional or short-term users.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Closed front vs Open front:&lt;/em&gt; Open front generally gives better access for washing
and some toileting procedures. Closed front gives better support to the legs, and may 
be required for good positioning. Rear or side opening may be required depending on
the user's bowel management routine.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Size of Aperture:&lt;/em&gt; The default aperture sizes vary according to the manufacturer,
and the size of seat chosen (paedatric/junior/adult). A smaller aperture may be required 
for users who have wasting of their gluts (resulting in bony bottoms), as they may tend to sink too far down through
a large aperture, which is an issue for skin stretching and clearance to roll over the toilet.
Smaller apertures can also assist with maintaining posture.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. What seat padding will be needed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are usually at least two, and often three, standard levels of pressure redistribution
in shower commode seat ranges. The basic level might include a plastic, moulded foam, or machine-made ply and foam seat.
The next level up is generally a hand-made padded seat. The top level is called different things depending on
the manufacturer: "pressure care special", "Dartex" (has extra-stretchy black covering as well as extra foam), 
"JPTR", etc. The top level seats often have dual-layer foam and a stretchy covering. The foam is usually higher.
Keep this difference in mind if you need to specify the seat to floor height.
The vast majority of mobile shower commode users are catered for within this selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those with a very high risk of pressure injury, an extra pressure relief layer can be added, such 
as a gel commode seat topper (available in adult standard size only, closed and open front),
ROHO commode seat cushion (can be made to order), or I've cut a hole in an &lt;a href="http://otequip.info/2015/11/11/equagel-cushion.html"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Equagel cushion&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
which worked quite well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. How will the new piece of equipment fit into the user's lifestlye?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they travel?&lt;/em&gt; If so, a folding shower commode might be required. The ability to adjust the height may
also be useful. Depending on the circumstances, the user might have an ideal mobile 
shower commode for home use, and a more portable alternative for travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they have to sit for long periods?&lt;/em&gt; Users with neurogenic bowel, such as people with
spina bifida or spinal cord injury, may have to sit for long periods due to their bowel
routine. Sometimes, they may want the option of sitting somewhere other than the bathroom. 
A suitable pan and rack would be needed, and a splash guard. Unfortunately not many 
mobile shower commodes have options for the type of pan/bowl provided, so this may
involve some creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Who else lives in their household?&lt;/em&gt; This may impact on storage options. If the bathroom
is used by others, the mobile shower commode may need to be stored somewhere else.
It's good to have a plan for storage before the equipment arrives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10.  How are the user's needs likely to change over time?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine how the user is likely to change over the next few years, and
go back over all the questions above considering the possible changes. Will your 
original prescription still be valid? I look at getting adjustable features
to manage predicatable changes, such as growth in children. With children, we
plan for them to become more independent over time. For someone with a progressive
condition, the ideal shower commode will be easily modified in future with more
support, a higher pressure care seat, or other features they may benefit from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;* * *&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's the end of my "quick" guide to mobile shower commode prescription. They can
be quite straight-forward or a bit tricky to get right, depending on your level
of experience and the complexity of the user. If you're just starting out, it's a 
great idea to get someone to supervise your first few prescriptions, as mistakes can be very costly
and time consuming, not to mention embarrassing! I've been prescribing mobile shower commodes
regularly for 5 years and I still talk through most scripts with a colleague before
submitting them, especially the trickier ones. Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have some mobile shower commode tips - please share!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SmartDrive MX2 Review</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/11/26/smartdrivemx2.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/11/26/smartdrivemx2.html</id>
    <published>2015-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2015-12-09T06:51:26+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The SmartDrive is a power-assist device that attaches to a manual wheelchair. 
It works by adding a fifth, powered wheel to the rear of the chair. The wheel attachment
also houses the battery, so there is no need for a separate battery pack, as there was
with the original SmartDrive. The SmartDrive's power is controlled by a Bluetooth 
wristband that looks similar to a FitBit, which has an on/off/mode button and a movement sensor
that controls stop/go. Active wheelchair users may appreciate the added boost to their 
functional mobility in the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This video from &lt;a href="http://www.max-mobility.com/smartdrive#mx2"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Max Mobility&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
shows the SmartDrive MX2 in action:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe class="youtube" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8uIXemVXlD4?rel=0" width="853" height="480" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The info I'm providing here has come from a demo session with a supplier, the SmartDrive MX2 User Manual,
internet research, and stories from SBH Queensland therapists (Elizabeth Steele and Angela Tincknell) 
who have used the product with some clients, with varying outcomes.&lt;br /&gt;
If you have more or different information, please share it by commenting below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some specifications:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fitting:&lt;/em&gt; The SmartDrive unit clips into a clamp. Two different size clamps are available 
for fixed frame chairs (standard size fits up to 1in (25mm) diameter camber tube, larger size also available). 
Two different size adaptors are available for folding frame chairs (widths: 11-15in (28-38cm) and 15-19in (38-48cm)).
Only one clamp/bracket is supplied with the SmartDrive, so a choice must be made prior to ordering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Folding frame bracket for SmartDrive MX2" src="/2015/11/26/smartdrivemx2/smartdrivemx2-1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The folding-frame brackets cost about $300 as an upcharge, or more if purchased retrospectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Distance:&lt;/em&gt; Range of up to 20km (12 miles) per charge on fairly flat, easy terraine. Uphill uses more battery power. 
The wrist band should last about 10hrs per charge, and can be turned off when not in use to help it last longer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Weight rating:&lt;/em&gt; 14-150kg (30-331lb) user weight. No comment is made in the manual about whether this includes the
weight of the wheelchair.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unit Weight:&lt;/em&gt; 5.7kg (12.5lb). The brackets and clamps weigh up to 400g.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Charging the Drive Unit:&lt;/em&gt; While in use, the drive unit will beep when the battery depletes to 20% charge, to prompt recharging 
as soon as possible and avoid completely running out. There are 4 blue LEDs on the drive unit that indicate the 
level of charge remaining. To charge the drive unit, it must be plugged into a mains power outlet via the SmartDrive charging 
cable for approximately 3hrs for a full charge. There are 
LEDs on the charge box that indicate power/charging/fully charged. When the drive unit is on, 4 blue lights means fully charged.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Top view of SmartDriveMX2" src="/2015/11/26/smartdrivemx2/smartdrivemx2-2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Power button, charing port and LED configuration&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Charging the Wristband:&lt;/em&gt; When the wristband is in use, a low battery is indicated by the light flashing blue then red every 1.5sec. 
The wristband is chaged by USB, so can be plugged into a computer, car charger, or mains power outlet.
A full charge takes approximately 2.5hrs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wristband Details:&lt;/em&gt; The wristband is made from a flexible material, which feels like silicone or a similar polymer. 
The band is fairly easy to don. It involved opening the band, sliding hand through,
squeezing with other hand to slide the two sides of the band across eachother, then pushing the stopper through one of the slots.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Wristband at full open setting" src="/2015/11/26/smartdrivemx2/smartdrivemx2-4.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Wristband on maximum open setting&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Travel:&lt;/em&gt; The SmartDrive can be taken on aeroplanes as carry-on luggage. Due to the lithium-ion battery, 
placing the drive unit in checked baggage may not be allowed. 
A certificate can be downloaded from the Max Mobility website to show your airline.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warranty:&lt;/em&gt; 12 month manufacturers warranty.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Weather and Terrain:&lt;/em&gt; The SmartDrive is mainly intended for indoor and light outdoor use, e.g. shopping in town, 
getting around school/university/workplace, going for a walk down the street, etc. It isn't an "all terrain" option. 
The User Manual outlines conditions to avoid, such as icy surfaces, loose surface (sand, gravel etc), or standing water 
(puddles or pools). The rep we spoke to advised that small puddles after light rain would probably be OK.
This option wouldn't be suitable for hiking through the bush, using on the farm, or getting down to the beach. It might 
be OK on grass when used in combination with something like the Freewheel.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;em&gt;Cost:&lt;/em&gt; In Australia, approximately $8,500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Use the SmartDrive MX2:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wristband is the main control while using the SmartDrive MX2. It replaces the indoor/outdoor button on the 
original SmartDrive, and makes the unit more responsive. The terminology has also changed
from indoor/outdoor modes to training/everyday modes, though they are pretty much the same thing. The wristband has 
a coloured LED light that indicates the mode:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green = training (indoor) mode, which is very sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blue = everyday (outdoor) mode, which is less sensitive and faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Red = No go, drive unit off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No light = wrist band off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also gives feedback using vibration, but may be inconsistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the user has the SmartDrive attached to their wheelchair, wristband on wrist, and is ready to go, turn the wristband
on by pushing the button. Green mode should be activated. Green mode is
recommended for training beginners, and it would probably be the most appropriate setting for manoeuvring around people and furniture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When outdoors or needing more power, press and hold the button for 5 seconds, until the band vibrates and 
the light turns blue. Now, when the user pushes the wheels, the SmartDrive will maintain the top speed reached. 
The user should let the SmartDrive do all the propelling, but still keep their hands on the push rims for steering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In indoor (green) mode, you can stop the SmartDrive by holding the wheels 
or rims, as per normal manual wheelchair use. &lt;strong&gt;This will not work in 
outdoor mode.&lt;/strong&gt; To stop in outdoor (blue) mode, tap the wrist on the push rims. 
The SmartDrive will turn off, allowing the user to brake as they normally would, 
by holding the push rims. The wristband LED will be red.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the user pushes the wheels again, the SmartDrive will re-engage and return to blue mode. 
This can cause issues in some situations, such as negotiating an obstacle. 
In this case, once stopped, press the button and hold until the wristband is off. 
Turn it on again once after passing the obstacle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Wristband button and LED" src="/2015/11/26/smartdrivemx2/smartdrivemx2-3.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The button requires firm pressure&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SmartDrive MX2 may suit users who:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Live an active lifestyle in a reasonably urban environment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have good wheelchair skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have fast response times, reasonable cognition and sensible judgement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For any user, good training is particularly important. The SmartDrive MX2 isn't a product that can be picked up and used fully from the start.
As there is an extra step required to stop, practice is required before using the SmartDrive MX2 into the community. Conveniently,
a training guide is provided in the back of the User Manual. This is a good start. Clients of therapists I have spoken with have had minor accidents
using this equipment, even once they were familiar with it. For those who do learn to use it successfully, the SmartDrive can take the user's active lifestlye
to the next level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SmartDrive propelling uphill" src="/2015/11/26/smartdrivemx2/SmartDriveMX2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Image from Max Mobility website&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven't prescribed a SmartDrive MX2 yet, but when I do, I will be sure to have at least 1-2hrs 
of client use before prescribing, at least 1 hour set aside for training once they've got it, 
and a week or two of using in very low-risk environments before
taking it into the community. The extent of training required might be a drawback 
for some therapists (unless the supplier is willing and able to provide adequate training)
and the safety aspects may make this product unsuitable for users with slow processing or response times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have any further thoughts or questions about the SmartDrive MX2? 
Please comment - for the benefit of the OT community!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>EquaGel Cushion Review</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/11/11/equagel-cushion.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/11/11/equagel-cushion.html</id>
    <published>2015-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2015-11-18T12:47:06+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://equapressure.com/Cushions.html"&gt;&lt;u&gt;EquaGel cushion&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a relative 
newcomer to the Australian wheelchair pressure cushion 
market from Utah, USA. The "EquaGel" name was trademarked in 2011. 
It is on the Queensland Medical Aids Subsidy Scheme (MASS) Standing Offer 
Agreement (SOA) for wheelchair cushions, and costs about $250-$300.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first encountered this product at the Occupational Therapy Australia 2015 
national conference trade display. The man at the EquaGel stand, let's call him 
Bob, had an EquaGel General cushion sitting on a regular plastic chair. There 
were a set of car keys on the cushion. "Sit down," Bob said. "Sit on the cushion 
and tell me if you can feel the keys." I was sceptical and uninspired by the idea
of hard car keys jabbing my gluteus maximus. However, I took Bob up on his challenge,
and gently lowered myself into the seat. I was pleasantly surprised. The keys &lt;em&gt;were not&lt;/em&gt; 
uncomfortable to sit on; I couldn't even locate them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="EquaGel General Cushion from front" src="/2015/11/11/equagel-cushion/equagel1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Equagel General cushion in 16x16in (40x40cm)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bob went on to explain that the cushion is made from a patented polymer gel. 
It is a synthetic product; latex free. The key to EquaGel's pressure redistribution
qualities, though, is the column buckling effect. The Equagel website explains
this in detail, but basically the cushion has two layers, the top has a grid of 
1cm cells, and the bottom layer has a grid of 2.5cm cells. When a 
certain amount of pressure is applied to a column from the top, it collapses, allowing
the weight to be shared across to adjacent columns, and the user to sink into the cushion. However,
the elastic quality of the gel is always wanting to help the columns reform to
their propper shape, which provides an upwards force, preventing bottoming out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Column grid on the top layer of the cushion" src="/2015/11/11/equagel-cushion/equagel2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;View from top, grid of 1cm columns&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Column grid of the bottom layer" src="/2015/11/11/equagel-cushion/equagel5.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;View of underside, grid of 2.5cm columns. The columns underneath have more 
robust walls, lending structural stability to the easily conforming top layer columns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cushion has been moulded to included a sacral/ischial well at the rear of 
the cushion. The well assists with redistributing pressure from high risk areas 
to the thighs and greater trochanters. It also assists
with positioning and maintaining posture, preventing the user from sliding forward.
Overall, I've rated the EquaGel general cushion as providing moderate pressure redistribution 
qualities, and moderate postural support due to the well and the amount of immersion.
See how it compares to other in the OT Equipment Info &lt;a href="http://otequip.info/2015/08/15/wheelchair-cushion-guide.html"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Quick Guide to Wheelchair Cushions&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The well is 1.7cm lower than the rest of the cushion" src="/2015/11/11/equagel-cushion/equagel3.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The two layers thin at the back to create a well. General cushion height: 
5.1cm, Well height: 3.4cm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cushion cover has been thoughtfully designed. It has a label on the left side 
to assist users to orientate the cushion correctly (assuming the cover has been 
put on correctly), a zip and a handle on the back, and Velcro on the base to keep
it in place. The outer fabric is soft and stretchy. The inside top of the cover 
has a course-weave cotton lining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Equagel cushion cover design features" src="/2015/11/11/equagel-cushion/equagel4.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far I've used this cushion much more &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; the cover. Uncovered, the 
cushion lends itself nicely to use in the shower. The open column design means that 
water can easily drain though, and the distributer assured me that the warm 
water will not damage the gel polymer. I have even cut a hole out of the middle so it 
could be used on a mobile shower commode. This was a quicker, easier, and more accurate 
solution than ordering a custom shower commode seat of another brand (e.g. ROHO). The columns maintain 
their structural integrity, and the centre piece can be used for other applications,
such as heel protection, or reinserted to be used on a wheelchair or standard
shower chair. The weight and slight stickiness of the gel has meant it stays in 
place on the commode seat without adhesives, though it needs to be well positioned
before the user sits on it, as it can tend to stretch or move out of shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things I like about the EquaGel cushion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The design is innovative, very clever, and effective for moderate pressure redistribution.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is versatile: it can be used on a regular chair/wheelchair, and in the shower or other wet areas (allowing adequate drying time in the shade to prevent it becoming mouldy).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The design allows for air flow through the cushion, providing assistance with moisture management. It would do well at protecting the skin from incontinence, 
however it wouldn't protect the wheelchair.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is good value, priced similar to a high quality foam cushion, but I suspect it is more durable than foam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possible drawbacks for the EquaGel cushion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is rather heavy, which is a common issue for gel cushions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Its ability to easily conform can make handling difficult (it's very floppy). This can make it difficult to get the cover on and off.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The two points above would make me think twice before considering suggesting this cushion to a user with low hand strength who would need to manage the cushion independently.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Smallest size is 16x16in (40x40cm), no paediatric sizes available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Note: MASS won't fund the cushion for shower use, especially if you're going to cut a hole in it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are your thoughts on the EquaGel cushion? Now it's your turn to share…&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>DTVP-2 vs DTVP-3: A Worthwhile Upgrade?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/10/24/dtvp2-vs-dtvp3.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/10/24/dtvp2-vs-dtvp3.html</id>
    <published>2015-10-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2015-12-31T03:36:27+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Developmental Test of Visual Perception (DTVP)&lt;/em&gt; has been around a long time. It was 
developed my Marianne Frostig and colleagues in the early 1960s, and first standardised in 1963.
The DTVP-2 was released in 1993, and most recently, the Third Edition of the DTVP
was published by &lt;a href="http://www.proedinc.com/customer/ProductView.aspx?ID=5697&amp;amp;sSearchWord="&gt;&lt;u&gt;Pro-Ed&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
in 2014 with updated norms. But has much really changed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Examiner Record Booklets" src="/2015/10/24/dtvp2-vs-dtvp3/dtvp2vsdtvp3.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the "official" list of changes on the publisher's website, so I'm 
not going to repeat that, but instead share my experience.
My workplace has purchased the DTVP-3 at the start of 2015. At first glance, it 
appeared to me that the packaging had just been made more colourful, and a few 
of the subtests removed. However, having now used it, I am thankful for the small 
changes that have made the assessment much easier to administer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things to like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Visual-Motor Speed and Position in Space subtests are gone! I used to get 
frustrated marking these, as the marking criteria was very strict about where the 
pencil marks were allowed to be. I felt the children were losing marks unfairly,
as the aim of the Speed subtest is to mark as many shapes as possible, but the shape
wouldn't count if the mark protuded outside the shape.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Removed Subtests" src="/2015/10/24/dtvp2-vs-dtvp3/cutsubtests.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Removed Subtests: Visual-Motor Speed and Spatial Relations&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not only has removal of three subtests (Position in Space, Spatial Relations, 
and Visual-Motor Speed) meant shorter administration time, the change in order
has helped test administration run more smoothly. No longer do we need to switch 
between the response booklet and the stimulus booklet for each subtest.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The layout of the Examiner record form has become much more user-friendly. It
now includes the standard wording for explaining the tasks, and the responses are
much easier to instantly mark correct or incorrect by the bolding of correct responses.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Inside Examiner Record Booklets" src="/2015/10/24/dtvp2-vs-dtvp3/examinerform.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Completely new layout of the Examiner Record Booklet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The layout of the Response Booklet has been improved. There is now more space between items.
Some of the pictures in the Eye-Hand Coordination Subtest have changed, fairly inconsequentially.
The Copying Subtest has been reordered to better reflect the developmental progression of
drawing skills. Scoring this subtest has also been much improved with provision of
a Scoring Template, which includes all the necessary angles and measuring lines for accurate scoring.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Improvements to the Copying Subtest" src="/2015/10/24/dtvp2-vs-dtvp3/copying_subtest.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Improvements to the Copying Subtest&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Even the Stimulus Booklet has had a facelift. It now includes the letters corresponding to
the answers, under each figure. I've found it useful to double-check sometimes if
the child points too quickly by saying "was that 'B' and 'F'?" There are some new items,
and all the items now have the potential answers layed out in a single row.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Updated Stimulus Layout" src="/2015/10/24/dtvp2-vs-dtvp3/updatedlayout.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Updated layout of Stimulus Booklet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Norms are now provided up to 12 years 11 months. I find this very convenient,
because the same assessment can be used in early primary school, and again for 
comparison around the age of transition to high school.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things to question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although this assessment has been around a long time, we are yet to have international
standardisation. The DTVP-3 boasts impressive reliability and "is shown to be unbiased 
relative to race, gender, and handedness." Is it valid for use with Australian children?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Was the removal of the Spatial Relations subtest beneficial? Was that data useful?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now there is no component taking into account the speed of visual-motor integration tasks.
Is speed of completion relevant in assessing proficiency? I would have thought so.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please share your thoughts. Comment below…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dictation with Dragon Naturally Speaking</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/09/11/dragon-dictation.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/09/11/dragon-dictation.html</id>
    <published>2015-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2015-10-28T04:44:27+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dragon Naturally Speaking, available from &lt;a href="http://shop.nuance.com/store/nuanceus/Custom/pbpage.resp-dragon-home-bf-2013-digital"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Nuance&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
has been around a fair while, and is one of the pioneers of voice to text technology. 
In this post, I'll share my learnings regarding Dragon Naturally Speaking Home 13.
I've used this application more than the free Dragon iPad/Android app because it doesn't 
require internet access and it has more features. I have also used Dragon Home 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why use dictation?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dictation is great for users who:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have reasonably good verbal language skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are unable to achieve efficient computer use due to a problem with their motor
skills (e.g. impairment of fine motor skills, or physical fatigue)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have the motivation and support to learn how to use it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Using dictation with Headset" src="/2015/09/11/dragon-dictation/plantronics-girl-1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have trialled dictation with a number of upper primary students and high school
students who had trouble getting their content down on the page. The idea of trying
dictation was that it would remove the burden of spelling and physically writing the words,
allowing greater cognitive capacity for generating the content. Most of the trials 
showed that dictation wasn't the solution for these users, for the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dictation requires much greater cognitive capacity (at least initially) to structure
content before saying it, and/or to develop a new work-flow.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It requires good verbal and written language skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The equipment requires more set up than not using it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It has to be done in a quiet environment, so it's virtually impossible to use 
in a classroom. Even if the classroom is quiet, the student doesn't want everyone
to hear what they're working on.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Often the students found it easier to type.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The problem in generating content was with their cognitive skills rather than
their motor skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideal user for dictation software (that an OT would work with) is someone who
prefers to use their verbal skills over their fine motor skills, or doesn't have
the option. I have seen Dragon Naturally Speaking used very effectively by a young
man with no use of his arms. It was his only option to connect with his web-based 
community, and he used it seamlessly, faster than someone using a keyboard and mouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dragon Naturally Speaking" src="/2015/09/11/dragon-dictation/dns-home-lg-banner.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dragon Naturally Speaking is still my preferred software option at the moment.
It is very practical for everyday school or work life. It integrates well with 
your usual programs, such as Microsoft Office, emails and web browsers. There 
will be whole lot more competitors to watch out for as voice control is turning
mainstream, with services such as Siri (Apple), Google Now, Cortana, and Hound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What have been your experiences with dictation software/hardware? Leave a comment…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
