<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2015-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>EquaGel Cushion Review</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/11/11/equagel-cushion.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/11/11/equagel-cushion.html</id>
    <published>2015-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2015-11-18T12:36:33+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://equapressure.com/Cushions.html"&gt;&lt;u&gt;EquaGel cushion&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a relative 
newcomer to the Australian wheelchair pressure cushion 
market from Utah, USA. The "EquaGel" name was trademarked in 2011. 
It is on the Queensland Medical Aids Subsidy Scheme (MASS) Standing Offer 
Agreement (SOA) for wheelchair cushions, and costs about $250-$300.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first encountered this product at the Occupational Therapy Australia 2015 
national conference trade display. The man at the EquaGel stand, let's call him 
Bob, had an EquaGel General cushion sitting on a regular plastic chair. There 
were a set of car keys on the cushion. "Sit down," Bob said. "Sit on the cushion 
and tell me if you can feel the keys." I was sceptical and uninspired by the idea
of hard car keys jabbing my gluteus maximus. However, I took Bob up on his challenge,
and gently lowered myself into the seat. I was pleasantly surprised. The keys &lt;em&gt;were not&lt;/em&gt; 
uncomfortable to sit on; I couldn't even locate them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="EquaGel General Cushion from front" src="/images/2015-11-11-equagel/equagel1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Equagel General cushion in 16x16in (40x40cm)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bob went on to explain that the cushion is made from a patented polymer gel. 
It is a synthetic product; latex free. The key to EquaGel's pressure redistribution
qualities, though, is the column buckling effect. The Equagel website explains
this in detail, but basically the cushion has two layers, the top has a grid of 
1cm cells, and the bottom layer has a grid of 2.5cm cells. When a 
certain amount of pressure is applied to a column from the top, it collapses, allowing
the weight to be shared across to adjacent columns, and the user to sink into the cushion. However,
the elastic quality of the gel is always wanting to help the columns reform to
their propper shape, which provides an upwards force, preventing bottoming out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Column grid on the top layer of the cushion" src="/images/2015-11-11-equagel/equagel2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;View from top, grid of 1cm columns&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Column grid of the bottom layer" src="/images/2015-11-11-equagel/equagel5.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;View of underside, grid of 2.5cm columns. The columns underneath have more 
robust walls, lending structural stability to the easily conforming top layer columns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cushion has been moulded to included a sacral/ischial well at the rear of 
the cushion. The well assists with redistributing pressure from high risk areas 
to the thighs and greater trochanters. It also assists
with positioning and maintaining posture, preventing the user from sliding forward.
Overall, I've rated the EquaGel general cushion as providing moderate pressure redistribution 
qualities, and moderate postural support due to the well and the amount of immersion.
See how it compares to other in the OT Equipment Info &lt;a href="http://otequip.info/2015/08/15/wheelchair-cushion-guide.html"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Quick Guide to Wheelchair Cushions&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The well is 1.7cm lower than the rest of the cushion" src="/images/2015/11/11/equagel/equagel3.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The two layers thin at the back to create a well. General cushion height: 
5.1cm, Well height: 3.4cm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cushion cover has been thoughtfully designed. It has a label on the left side 
to assist users to orientate the cushion correctly (assuming the cover has been 
put on correctly), a zip and a handle on the back, and Velcro on the base to keep
it in place. The outer fabric is soft and stretchy. The inside top of the cover 
has a course-weave cotton lining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Equagel cushion cover design features" src="/images/2015/11/11/equagel/equagel4.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far I've used this cushion much more &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; the cover. Uncovered, the 
cushion lends itself nicely to use in the shower. The open column design means that 
water can easily drain though, and the distributer assured me that the warm 
water will not damage the gel polymer. I have even cut a hole out of the middle so it 
could be used on a mobile shower commode. This was a quicker, easier, and more accurate 
solution than ordering a custom shower commode seat of another brand (e.g. ROHO). The columns maintain 
their structural integrity, and the centre piece can be used for other applications,
such as heel protection, or reinserted to be used on a wheelchair or standard
shower chair. The weight and slight stickiness of the gel has meant it stays in 
place on the commode seat without adhesives, though it needs to be well positioned
before the user sits on it, as it can tend to stretch or move out of shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things I like about the EquaGel cushion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The design is innovative, very clever, and effective for moderate pressure redistribution.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is versatile: it can be used on a regular chair/wheelchair, and in the shower or other wet areas (allowing adequate drying time in the shade to prevent it becoming mouldy).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The design allows for air flow through the cushion, providing assistance with moisture management. It would do well at protecting the skin from incontinence, 
however it wouldn't protect the wheelchair.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is good value, priced similar to a high quality foam cushion, but I suspect it is more durable than foam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possible drawbacks for the EquaGel cushion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is rather heavy, which is a common issue for gel cushions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Its ability to easily conform can make handling difficult (it's very floppy). This can make it difficult to get the cover on and off.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The two points above would make me think twice before considering suggesting this cushion to a user with low hand strength who would need to manage the cushion independently.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Smallest size is 16x16in (40x40cm), no paediatric sizes available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Note: MASS won't fund the cushion for shower use, especially if you're going to cut a hole in it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are your thoughts on the EquaGel cushion? Now it's your turn to share…&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>DTVP-2 vs DTVP-3: A Worthwhile Upgrade?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/10/24/dtvp2-vs-dtvp3.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/10/24/dtvp2-vs-dtvp3.html</id>
    <published>2015-10-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2015-10-28T04:46:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Developmental Test of Visual Perception (DTVP)&lt;/em&gt; has been around a long time. It was 
developed my Marianne Frostig and colleagues in the early 1960s, and first standardised in 1963.
The DTVP-2 was released in 1993, and most recently, the Third Edition of the DTVP
was published by &lt;a href="http://www.proedinc.com/customer/ProductView.aspx?ID=5697&amp;amp;sSearchWord="&gt;&lt;u&gt;Pro-Ed&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
in 2014 with updated norms. But has much really changed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Examiner Record Booklets" src="/2015/10/24/dtvp2-vs-dtvp3/dtvp2vsdtvp3.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the "official" list of changes on the publisher's website, so I'm 
not going to repeat that, but instead share my experience.
My workplace has purchased the DTVP-3 at the start of 2015. At first glance, it 
appeared to me that the packaging had just been made more colourful, and a few 
of the subtests removed. However, having now used it, I am thankful for the small 
changes that have made the assessment much easier to administer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things to like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Visual-Motor Speed and Position in Space subtests are gone! I used to get 
frustrated marking these, as the marking criteria was very strict about where the 
pencil marks were allowed to be. I felt the children were losing marks unfairly,
as the aim of the Speed subtest is to mark as many shapes as possible, but the shape
wouldn't count if the mark protuded outside the shape.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Removed Subtests" src="/2015/10/24/dtvp2-vs-dtvp3/cutsubtests.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Removed Subtests: Visual-Motor Speed and Position in Space&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not only has removal of three subtests (Position in Space, Spatial Relations, 
and Visual-Motor Speed) meant shorter administration time, the change in order
has helped test administration run more smoothly. No longer do we need to switch 
between the response booklet and the stimulus booklet for each subtest.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The layout of the Examiner record form has become much more user-friendly. It
now includes the standard wording for explaining the tasks, and the responses are
much easier to instantly mark correct or incorrect by the bolding of correct responses.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Inside Examiner Record Booklets" src="/2015/10/24/dtvp2-vs-dtvp3/examinerform.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Completely new layout of the Examiner Record Booklet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The layout of the Response Booklet has been improved. There is now more space between items.
Some of the pictures in the Eye-Hand Coordination Subtest have changed, fairly inconsequentially.
The Copying Subtest has been reordered to better reflect the developmental progression of
drawing skills. Scoring this subtest has also been much improved with provision of
a Scoring Template, which includes all the necessary angles and measuring lines for accurate scoring.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Improvements to the Copying Subtest" src="/2015/10/24/dtvp2-vs-dtvp3/copying_subtest.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Improvements to the Copying Subtest&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Even the Stimulus Booklet has had a facelift. It now includes the letters corresponding to
the answers, under each figure. I've found it useful to double-check sometimes if
the child points too quickly by saying "was that 'B' and 'F'?" There are some new items,
and all the items now have the potential answers layed out in a single row.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Updated Stimulus Layout" src="/2015/10/24/dtvp2-vs-dtvp3/updatedlayout.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Updated layout of Stimulus Booklet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Norms are now provided up to 12 years 11 months. I find this very convenient,
because the same assessment can be used in early primary school, and again for 
comparison around the age of transition to high school.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things to question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although this assessment has been around a long time, we are yet to have international
standardisation. The DTVP-3 boasts impressive reliability and "is shown to be unbiased 
relative to race, gender, and handedness." Is it valid for use with Australian children?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Was the removal of the Spatial Relations subtest beneficial? Was that data useful?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now there is no component taking into account the speed of visual-motor integration tasks.
Is speed of completion relevant in assessing proficiency? I would have thought so.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please share your thoughts. Comment below…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dictation with Dragon Naturally Speaking</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/09/11/dragon-dictation.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/09/11/dragon-dictation.html</id>
    <published>2015-09-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2015-10-28T04:44:27+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dragon Naturally Speaking, available from &lt;a href="http://shop.nuance.com/store/nuanceus/Custom/pbpage.resp-dragon-home-bf-2013-digital"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Nuance&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
has been around a fair while, and is one of the pioneers of voice to text technology. 
In this post, I'll share my learnings regarding Dragon Naturally Speaking Home 13.
I've used this application more than the free Dragon iPad/Android app because it doesn't 
require internet access and it has more features. I have also used Dragon Home 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why use dictation?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dictation is great for users who:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have reasonably good verbal language skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are unable to achieve efficient computer use due to a problem with their motor
skills (e.g. impairment of fine motor skills, or physical fatigue)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have the motivation and support to learn how to use it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Using dictation with Headset" src="/2015/09/11/dragon-dictation/plantronics-girl-1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have trialled dictation with a number of upper primary students and high school
students who had trouble getting their content down on the page. The idea of trying
dictation was that it would remove the burden of spelling and physically writing the words,
allowing greater cognitive capacity for generating the content. Most of the trials 
showed that dictation wasn't the solution for these users, for the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dictation requires much greater cognitive capacity (at least initially) to structure
content before saying it, and/or to develop a new work-flow.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It requires good verbal and written language skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The equipment requires more set up than not using it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It has to be done in a quiet environment, so it's virtually impossible to use 
in a classroom. Even if the classroom is quiet, the student doesn't want everyone
to hear what they're working on.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Often the students found it easier to type.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The problem in generating content was with their cognitive skills rather than
their motor skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideal user for dictation software (that an OT would work with) is someone who
prefers to use their verbal skills over their fine motor skills, or doesn't have
the option. I have seen Dragon Naturally Speaking used very effectively by a young
man with no use of his arms. It was his only option to connect with his web-based 
community, and he used it seamlessly, faster than someone using a keyboard and mouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dragon Naturally Speaking" src="/2015/09/11/dragon-dictation/dns-home-lg-banner.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dragon Naturally Speaking is still my preferred software option at the moment.
It is very practical for everyday school or work life. It integrates well with 
your usual programs, such as Microsoft Office, emails and web browsers. There 
will be whole lot more competitors to watch out for as voice control is turning
mainstream, with services such as Siri (Apple), Google Now, Cortana, and Hound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What have been your experiences with dictation software/hardware? Leave a comment…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Jay J2 Cushion Review</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/08/22/jay2-cushion.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/08/22/jay2-cushion.html</id>
    <published>2015-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2015-10-28T04:43:59+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Jay cushion range, available from &lt;a href="http://www.sunrisemedical.com.au/products/jay/wheelchair-cushions/jay-j2.aspx"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Sunrise Medical&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
is a tried and true pillar of the wheelchair cushion world. While the J2 isn't suitable for &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; application, it allows
easy customisation with modular components, and the design works well for users
of many shapes, sizes, and postures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The J2 range is quite comprehensive. The cushion shown is the standard J2. The 
J2 Deep Contour is another variant, which I have found to be a great cushion if more 
immersion is required, such as when the ischial tuberosities are particularly 
prominent. The J2 is available in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Widths: 14-24 inches (36-61cm)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depths: 14-20 inches (36-51cm)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Height: 2.5 inches (6.5cm)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Jay J2 Cushion side view" src="/2015/08/22/jay2-cushion/jay2-side.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;J2 cushion side view, 16 inches (406mm) deep by 14 inches (355mm) wide&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The widths and depths are customisable too. For example, I have ordered an 18-inch width
where the well size was the same as the 15.5-inch cushion. The supplier added a 
1-inch strip of foam to each side at no extra cost. I also love that if you (the OT or PT) 
are doing your own customisations on the foam base and it all goes horribly pear-shaped,
Sunrise will replace it free of charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Jay J2 Cushion Components" src="/2015/08/22/jay2-cushion/jay2-components.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;What's in the Box: Base, fluid tripad, and cover 
are essential components. The fluid supplement pad and adductor wedges are examples 
of the many modular components available to assist with postural management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When opening up a J2 cushion box, you will find the cushion (firm foam base, 
fluid pad and cover), plus any accessories ordered. Accessories such as the adductor wedges
or obliquity wedges come in pairs. The fluid supplement pads can be oridered 
individually and placed anywhere you like. I have found that you need to BYO additional
adhesive Velcro and some scissors when setting up a J2 with additional postural components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As there can be a bit of a delay between trialing the cushion with a user and 
their own cushion actually arriving, I've found that taking before and after photos 
of the user's posture, and taking photos of the set-up of the cushion at the stage 
where everyone was happy, is a great habit. When it comes time to configure
cushion, I've got a reminder of what went where!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Jay J2 Base Measurements" src="/2015/08/22/jay2-cushion/jay2-base.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The base has a large, deep well at the rear, allowing the user's bony prominences
(ischial tuberosities, sacrum and coccyx) to sink into the fluid. The lack of a 
firm back wall on the base removes all rub points for the sacrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The base is very firm foam; it has about as much give as polystyrene, but is much 
more durable. Some people wonder at how this firm foam can give such great 
pressure redistrubtion. The answer is the smart design. The contouring of the well,
its shape and size, takes pressure off the ischial tuberosities (ITs) and tailbone, and
shifts the weight-bearing to the greater trochanters (GTs) and the femurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GTs and the femurs are protected by the layer of softer foam built into
the fluid tripad. The ITs and tailbone are immersed in a fluid gel. The "tripad"
is named such because it has three comparments (one for each risk area), which helps
to stop the fluid migrating. That said, the fluid can still move about a fair bit. 
Whenever I prescribe this cuchion, I am sure to tell the users that they need to 
check the fluid every day and push it back towards the middle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The firm base at the front of the cushion is often appeciated by wheelchair users
who side-transfer, because they can wriggle their bottom forward and sit well-supported
on the front before moving themselves sideways onto the other seat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fluid tripad is itself customisable. It can be ordered with a specified percentage
overfill, or underfill, and this can be specified for each compartment. For example,
you could ask for 20% overfill all round for a user with a very bony bottom, or 10%
overfill on one side to help correct a subtle pelvic obliquity. If a lot more gel is needed,
you can call in the fluid supplement pad. I just love how easy this cushion is to 
configure in a million different ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Jay J2 Cover and Underside" src="/2015/08/22/jay2-cushion/jay2-underside.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The standard stretch cover is quick and easy to put on and remove. It is elasticated like
a fitted bedsheet. Velcro on the underside of the base and cover stops the cushion
sliding on the wheelchair seat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cushion cover is nice and simple. The stretchy, soft fabric seems to deal very 
well with sweat in our warm sub-tropical climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential downsides to be aware of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It's pretty heavy, weighing 3-5kg. Not the heaviest around, but I wouldn't call it a light-weight cushion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The fluid pad occasionally bursts, so it loses some points on durability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It requires daily maintenance (pushing the fluid back to the centre of the well)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Need to keep an eye on potential pressure areas under GTs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It doesn't come in paediatric sizes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main benefits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It has a great design for pressure management of ITs and sacrum/coccyx&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is easy to customise to accommodate or correct sitting posture, including pelvic obliquity, tilt and rotation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It comes in a wide variety of sizes and configurations for adults and teens&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is fairly easy to clean and maintain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How have you used the J2 cushion? Do you have any tips or stories to share? 
Leave a comment…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Quick Guide to Wheelchair Cushions</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/08/15/wheelchair-cushion-guide.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/08/15/wheelchair-cushion-guide.html</id>
    <published>2015-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2015-11-18T11:24:07+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Anyone who needs to use a wheelchair long-term should also be using a cushion on their
wheelchair, due to impaired mobility, sensation, or both. Wheelchair cushions reduce 
the risk of developing a pressure injury and provide postural support.
If the user doesn't have impaired mobility or sensation, a cushion will 
at least improve the comfort of the wheelchair. The levels of pressure 
redistribution and postural support vary a lot between different types of
cushions. These two factors are the first that I consider when choosing cushions
to trial. The table below is a very basic comparison of the different types of 
cushions. It's my general opinion, formed over several years of prescribing
cushions for wheelchair users. It's not an all-inclusive list, just the cushions
I've come across most often. I intend to add more to this table as I become
familiar with a wider range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;High-level Pressure Redistribution&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Moderate Pressure Redistribution&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Basic Pressure Redistribution&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High-level Postural Support&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Jay J2 range, &lt;br /&gt;Jay J3 range, &lt;br /&gt;ROHO Hybrid Elite&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ROHO Nexus SPIRIT, &lt;br /&gt;ROHO Harmony, &lt;br /&gt;Varilite Evolution&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moderate Postural Support&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ROHO Quadtro Select, &lt;br /&gt;ROHO Dual Valve&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ottobock Cloud, &lt;br /&gt;Varilite Meridian, &lt;br /&gt;EquaGel General&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Contoured Foam (e.g. ROHO Airlite, Invacare Matrx PS, Jay Zip), &lt;br /&gt;Stimulite Contoured&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Basic Postural Support&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ROHO Single Valve&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ROHO Mosaic, &lt;br /&gt;Action Gel&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;HEAPS in this category!&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Block of Foam  &lt;br /&gt;(e.g. Jay Basic, Ottobock Combifoam, Invacare Matrx Absolute) &lt;br /&gt;Stimulite Classic &amp;amp; Slimline, &lt;br /&gt;Varilite Zoid PSV, &lt;br /&gt;Basic Fibre-filled Cushions…&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To assess the level of pressure redistribution the user needs in a cushion, I
would do a recognised assessment such as a Waterlow Scale, or an informal 
assessment. Either way, main factors to consider include duration of sitting (mobility),
history of pressure areas, general health, amount of "bottom padding" (someone who
is very bony or very overweight generally has higher risk), and skin integrity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To assess the level of postural support/adjustment required, I would consider
balance, core strength, symmetry (scoliosis, pelvic obliquity, pelvic rotation), 
sitting posture when unsupported (if possible). If the user sits asymmetrically
I would generally look at prescribing one of the cushions I've listed in the
high-level postural support category because most of them are relatively easy to
customise to suit the users needs. For someone who tends to sacral sit (C-curve of
the back), a wedge under almost any cushion to bring their knees up relative to
their hips is worth a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other factors to consider when choosing a cushion include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incontinence: look for a waterproof, easy to clean cover; make sure you get a
spare cover, or consider a cushion design that's very easy to clean, such as the
Stimulite or Equagel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weight: for someone who has spent a lot to purchase an ultra-lightweight wheelchair,
consider avoiding a heavy gel cushion. Likewise, if the user will be lifting
the cushion on and off the chair regularly (e.g. for transporting in the car).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maintenance &amp;amp; Durability: Some cushions require regular maintenance and monitoring to check
they are working optimally (e.g. ROHO), whereas others just need the cover washed
occasionally. Choose a cushion that the user(s) can manage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important thing in choosing a cushion is to &lt;strong&gt;try it out!&lt;/strong&gt; Having the user
trial it, even for a few minutes, can save a lot of time down the track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Wheelchair with cushion" src="/2015/08/15/wheelchair-cushion-guide/wheelchair-beach.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The right wheelchair with the right cushion can bring freedom&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What other factors have impacted on your cushion choices? Leave a comment…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Welcome to OT Equipment Info</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/08/12/welcome.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/08/12/welcome.html</id>
    <published>2015-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2015-08-16T09:45:04+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A place for sharing ideas and experiences with equipment.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were to look at a day in the life of an occupational therapist (OT), 
there's a good chance you'd come across specialised assistive equipment somewhere. 
OTs help people overcome obstacles such as illness, injury or disability to 
achieve a lifestlye that is meaningful to them. We do this by either &lt;em&gt;remediating&lt;/em&gt; 
the problem, that is, helping the person recover, or &lt;em&gt;compensating&lt;/em&gt; for the problem,
by finding a way to work around it. We love presribing equipment because [when done well]
it provides a way for people to do things independently, or with less assistance 
than they would otherwise need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some benefits of using assistive equipment include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enabling someone to do something they otherwise wouldn't be able to,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reducing the need for assistance, thereby preserving dignity and enhancing
self-efficacy,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving safety and decreasing risk of injury to the person and others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choosing the right equipment can be a tedious task. OTs often have specific
measurements or features in mind that would promote the best possible outcome. 
The aim of &lt;strong&gt;OT Equipment Info&lt;/strong&gt; is to make it easy for OTs to find information;
saving time and improving outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
