<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2016-07-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Working Holiday in the UK - Part 2</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2016/07/11/working-holiday2.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2016/07/11/working-holiday2.html</id>
    <published>2016-07-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2016-08-09T15:48:01+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;While Australian health professionals are rarely denied 
registration, the application is definitely &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; quick and easy. I started the process 
in July 2015, and was granted my registration on 9th February, 2016. 
From start to finish, my application took about &lt;strong&gt;7 months&lt;/strong&gt;.
It doesn’t “usually” take that long, but it easily can. To work in the United Kingdom 
as an Occupational Therapist, Physiotherapist, 
Speech &amp;amp; Language Therapist, Paramedic, Clinical Scientist, Dietician, Podiatrist,
Psychologist, Social Worker, or other allied health professional, Health and Care Professions 
Council (HCPC) registration is essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HCPC have virtually the same role as the Australian Health Practitioners Regulation 
Agency (AHPRA). They ensure that health professionals uphold quality standards and follow the law. 
To be registered to practice in the UK, you need to apply to the HCPC. I was told the process 
can take up to six months, so I completed my HCPC application as the first step in 
process of moving. I didn't want to book flights etc, and then find that I'd be unable 
to work as an OT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="HCPC London" src="/2016/07/11/working-holiday2/hcpc-london.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I completed my Occupational Therapy degree in Australia, so I had to complete an 
International application for registration. The application form is available on 
the &lt;a href="http://www.hcpc-uk.org/apply/international/"&gt;&lt;u&gt;HCPC website&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and includes a 
list of what needs to be submitted. Keep in mind that the requirements could change 
and I am writing this about my own experience, so be sure to follow the HCPC guidance 
notes, which can be found following the application form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Parts of the application:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Application Form:&lt;/em&gt; This is about 12 pages that I had to fill in about myself.&lt;br /&gt;
My contact details etc., were fairly straightforward. Providing information about 
my previous OT jobs strained my brain a bit, and having to handwrite it on the 
application form feels like extra pressure to get it right the first time. When describing my previous OT roles, 
I just wrote a simple introductory sentence, followed by a list of what my work involved. The lists included the client 
group, assessments (formal and informal), interventions, evaluation, and extra things 
like group programs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Course Details Form:&lt;/em&gt; This may sound easy, but it's actually quite complicated. 
It must be completed by the university, in my case, the 
University of Queensland. They have staff in the therapies admin team who take care 
of these forms. It cost $165 and I had to provide details of all prac experiences 
(including first and second years) and electives. UQ sent me a form to fill out, to 
enable them to complete their form. The HCPC aren't interested in your academic 
transcript, but it might be handy to refer to this to check all your elective subjects 
are correct. It took a week or two for UQ to complete the form once I had provided all my course details.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Professional References:&lt;/em&gt; This can be tricky if you’re trying not to inform your 
current employer about your intention to move overseas, but you need someone from 
your most recent workplace to complete the reference, such as a team leader or senior OT. 
The application form provides two reference forms and says you need to submit at least 
one. I had been in the same job for a few years, and my work was quite classic OT
practice, so I just submitted one, completed by my team leader, a physiotherapist. 
I think the point of this form is to prove that you are working as an occupational 
therapist in a "safe and effective" manner. If I was working in a role that wasn’t 
a traditional OT role, or if "Occupaitonal Therapist" wasn't my job title, I might've 
got a second reference from a previous job to show I had “traditional” OT skills.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Personal Reference:&lt;/em&gt;  I asked a family friend, who is a church minister, to complete 
this part for me. There is a list of who can vouch for you as an upstanding citizen on the form.
The difficult part of this was just posting the form back and forwards, since they didn't live near me.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Certificate of professional status from the regulator in the country where you last practised”:&lt;/em&gt; 
This sounds complicated, but is very easy. There is a short form to fill out on the 
AHPRA website. It costs $50. They send the certificate directly to HCPC, electronically. 
I did this step aroundnthe time I posted the rest of the application so there wouldn't 
be too much of a gap between the two things arriving.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Payment (“Scrutiny Fee”) form:&lt;/em&gt; Fill out your credit card details or send a cheque/money 
order. Keep in mind that this will be an international transaction, in GBP, so you 
might want to check the conditions of your credit card to make sure you don’t get 
a nasty surprise. The fee is £495, which was about AU$1,000 when I applied.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Certified Copies of Important Documents:&lt;/em&gt; Be sure to read the guidance notes 
carefully on this one, as they need to be recently certified and have specific wording 
in the certification. They require:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Two identifying documents (e.g. passport / birth certificate / driver’s licence).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;If you have changed your name, certified evidence of this needs to be submitted (e.g. marriage certificate).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Certified copy of your qualification certificate (OT degree)&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Background Check Consent Form:&lt;/em&gt; I just filled it in and signed it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application form took me about 6-8 weeks to fully complete and submit. I sent 
the form to London by Australia Post’s CourierPost service, which offers a door 
to door tracking service. Then I waited about nine weeks, and nothing happened. 
I was really worried because the payment hadn’t been taken (which is meant to be 
the first step in the process).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Communication Breakdown&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I emailed them to check the status of my application, they reported they had 
emailed me earlier about the payment. I didn’t receive an email. Anyway, the cost 
of application processing changed after I signed the credit card payment authorisation, 
so that page was instantly shredded. I had to give my card details again, over a 
crackly international phone line. The payment went through instantly. The woman 
I first spoke to made a comment like “it’s a good thing they’ve actually got on 
with processing your application and not just left it sitting here waiting for payment.” 
But the next one said “Your application should be processed within twelve weeks.” 
I also got a letter in the post about a week later, saying again that it should 
be processed within twelve weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eleven weeks went by and I heard nothing. I emailed them again to check the status. 
Apparently. they had posted me a letter only two weeks after my payment to say 
that my application was approved, and I needed to phone them to arrange payment 
of my registration. I had not received the letter (though this was probably not 
HCPC’s fault, it happened with other mail too).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I phoned them, paid my registration fee, and I was so very relieved when my HCPC 
occupational therapy registration certificate and card arrived in the post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="HCPC Registered" src="/2016/07/11/working-holiday2/New-HCPC-Logo.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Cost of Registration:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applying for registration in the UK was more expensive than I expected. 
Here is the breakdown of my costs, in Australian dollars:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UQ Course Details Form Fee (money order): $173.95&lt;/li&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;AHPRA Certificate Fee: $50&lt;/li&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;Postage to London (CourierPost with tracking): $54.10&lt;/li&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;Application Scrutiny Fee: $1,072.58 (£495)&lt;/li&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;UK Registration Fee: $371.28, (£180) valid for 2 years&lt;/li&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total: $1,721.91&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, that's the story of how I got my HCPC registration. I hope that your story is 
short and sweet. Please post any questions and I'll try to reply quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or was your experience different to mine? Please share…&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Working Holiday in the UK - Part 1</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2016/06/26/working-holiday1.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2016/06/26/working-holiday1.html</id>
    <published>2016-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2016-06-26T20:01:50+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;While studying Occupational Therapy at university, it became clear that working 
in the UK or Ireland for a couple of years was a very common thing for OTs to do. 
It’s a well trodden path. It sounded so easy: just get a couple of years'
experience, and head on over there! It might even be a way of moving up career levels 
more quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="London" src="/2016/06/26/working-holiday1/london1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since I was a child, living overseas was one of my dreams. Growing up in Australia,
as a descendant of white invaders, I felt somewhat disconnected from parts of my
cultural heritage. We have developed a new heritage in Australia, which I love, but
not all of it makes sense. For example, Christmas is one of my favourite times of the year.
It’s normally sunny and humid. Backyard cricket is enjoyed with beer in hand, even when a
summer storm looms. Meanwhile, the cooks of the family are slaving away in a stuffy
kitchen over a hot stove to prepare the traditional baked ham/turkey/pork/chicken
or all the the above, with baked vegetables, while singing along to “I’m dreaming
of a white Christmas” and “dashing through the snow in a one horse open sleigh”. 
It just doesn’t add up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My husband and I decided in 2015 that the following year, 2016, was the time to 
make our move. The process involved applying for UK registration as an OT, applying
for visas, finding work, organising ourselves and our belongings, and working out
what to do about all those important extra bits and pieces, like insurance, phones,
etc. While most of it was fairly straightforward, it was difficult to find information
about what to do and when. For such a well trodden path, it doesn't seem particularly
well documented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, here is my story of moving from Australia to have a working holiday in the UK.
Since there is so much to write, it will be a 5 part series of posts. If you are
planning to do this, or something similar, be warned: there is a risk of drowning
in paperwork!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the main steps involved:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get your UK Occupational Therapy registration with the HCPC&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work out your plan (e.g. when will you finish work in Australia, fly over to UK, will you have a holiday in between… etc)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get your UK visa (if needed)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Register with recruitment agencies and proving your compliance with NHS policies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find somewhere to live, get settled in, start work, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions, please ask! Just remember that I’m not providing any
professional advice here, only sharing my experience, and the experiences others
have shared with me.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Miller Function &amp; Participation Scales (M-FUN-PS) Review</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2016/01/13/mfun.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2016/01/13/mfun.html</id>
    <published>2016-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2016-03-01T09:46:48+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Miller Function and Participation Scales (M-FUN-PS) is a standardised developmental 
assessment for children aged 2 years and 6 months, to 7 years and 11 months. It
covers three motor domains: visual motor (VM), fine motor (FM), and gross motor (GM),
as well as participation. The M-FUN-PS was authored by Dr Lucy Miller, a very 
experienced occupational therapist and researcher. 
Dr Miller has done a lot of work in the area of sensory processing disorder (SPD),
and has founded the SPD Foundation, the STAR Centre for SPD treatment, and the SPD
University, which provides online education to caregivers, the community, and health professionals. The M-FUN-PS
was published by &lt;a href="https://www.pearsonclinical.com.au/products/view/143#tabs=0"&gt;Pearson Clinical&lt;/a&gt; in 2006,
and can be purchased through the Pearson website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="M-FUN-PS Administration Directions" src="/2016/01/13/mfun/manual.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've been using the M-FUN-PS (or M-FUN for short) for about 18 months. We decided 
to purchase the M-FUN as a replacement for our old Peabody Developmental Motor Scales,
which had pieces missing and included some rather out-dated activities (which some may call "classic",
but we were finding children commonly found test materials unfamiliar). We wanted an
assessment that could provide detailed results for parents and teachers, with the child's transition
to school in mind. The main purpose for this assessment in my setting has been to
prepare for or assist the child's transition to their first year of formal schooling
("Prep" in Queensland).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The M-FUN is split into two age levels, 2yrs 6mths until the child turns 4, then 4yrs
until the child turns 8. As transition to school occurs in Queensland between 5yrs 6mths
and 6yrs 6mths, I have never administered the younger version of the assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Comparison of age groups" src="/2016/01/13/mfun/bunnies-puppies.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The two age groups complete the same items, with the tasks
simplified accordingly for the younger group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, it's quite a long and detailed assessment
to consider administering with such a young age group, particularly with children who have
developmental delays. Even the younger version includes letter writing, which I would
consider to be developmentally beyond that age group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Workbook covers" src="/2016/01/13/mfun/workbooks.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The workbooks and examiner forms are different for the lower 
and upper age ranges. The covers and layout are very motivating for children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The M-FUN kit includes many motivating and familiar items for children. The manipulatives (below)
come with the M-FUN set, or you can put together your own set by following the list in
the assessment manual. We found that we needed to replace some of the included items
with locally sources items, which worked better. For example, the "soft modelling clay"
included in our kit was rock hard, and even the therapists had trouble moulding it.
We have replaced it with standard plasticine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="M-FUN Manipulatives" src="/2016/01/13/mfun/manipulatives.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The M-FUN domains (Visual Motor, Fine Motor, and Gross Motor) are made up of multiple
games each. Each game is like a subtest all of its own, except the standard scores are
only available when scoring for every game of the domain is completed. Here is the
raw score table from the Examiner Form, which shows the games under each section:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Raw score table" src="/2016/01/13/mfun/itemslist.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's simulate one game from the fine motor domain to give you an idea of how the assessment is administered.
The game I've chosen is one that I find particularly challenging to administer. Not all
items are this complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Origami Game&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To prepare:&lt;/em&gt; Before the assessment session, you have removed the middle page
of the child's workbook and cut out the two origami templates. You also have 
your own origami templates, to use as a demo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You have on hand:&lt;/em&gt; the administration directions, the examiner record form, 
two terry towelling washcloths, your demo origami templates, the child's origami templates, and a stopwatch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Origami Demo" src="/2016/01/13/mfun/item-origamidemo.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Origami items for 4-7 year olds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Administer the items:&lt;/em&gt; Following the wording in the administration directions (below),
you complete the practice item with the child using the washcloths, followed by 
the dog origami, and the fish origami.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Origami Game Administration 1" src="/2016/01/13/mfun/item-dog.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Origami Game Administration 2" src="/2016/01/13/mfun/item-fish.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scoring:&lt;/em&gt; Now, I hope you were paying attention to the child's hand use and to the
30 second time limit. Work done after the time limit doesn't count. Here is the 
scoring to complete:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Origami Game Scoring Page" src="/2016/01/13/mfun/item-origamiscoring.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you've finished all items in the 25 page Examiner Form (below), you can score it all up
and get standardised scores for each of the three "Performance" domains, and use the examiner form and the
manual to decide whether the child is performing at an age-appropriate level, or 
whether the child's skill development is delayed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="M-FUN examiner form upper age group" src="/2016/01/13/mfun/examinerform.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Examiner Form for the upper age group&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can collect back the Home Observations Checklist from a parent, and the Classroom
Observations Checklist from the teacher, and compare the results to your Test Observations
Checklist. I believe these checklists are the same for both age groups. These provide the
measure of "Participation".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Observations Checklists" src="/2016/01/13/mfun/obs-checklists.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you've had a taste of how the M-FUN is administered, let me share my
experiences in using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Things to Like:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The assessment appeals to children. It is actually fun, as it was designed to be.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It gives you LOTS of information about the child's physical development and function.
The Neurological Foundations profile allows the examiner to perform deeper analysis of
the child's function, which can be particularly helpful for intervention planning.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is more holistic than other, similar assessments that concentrate solely on clinical acquisition of motor abilities.
The scores on the observations checklist can provide an indication as to how poor motor performance
affects their participation in the home and class settings. Again, this is very helpful for intervention planning.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The parts can be used separate from the whole assessment. For example, I can still
get standardised results for a child's VM and FM without doing the GM component or
observation checklists.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It covers all the basic skills I want to check for a child entering school, such as visual
scanning and tracking, pencil control, scissor skills, ability to sit at a table for
a length of time (45min), and following instructions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Things I Find Difficult:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While theoretically, this assessment can be done in a variety of settings (clinic,
home, school, etc.), this isn't always easy. I have found the gross motor section difficult,
as it requires prior set-up of measured lines and markers, and it requires a smooth wall
with a concrete floor against which a ball can be kicked for "Soccer". I've been unable to locate an
appropriate wall at several locations (homes and schools).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If one item in a performance domain can't be completed, a standard score for the
domain cannot be calculated. Therefore, if the only suitable wall becomes unavailable (e.g. it starts raining) for the
Soccer game, a standardised GM score can't be obtained even for the upper body items, and
the time you've spent on the rest of the GM section becomes much less useful.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To administer this assessment, you have to be very organised. As you may have noticed in the
Origami example above, there are many different resources to juggle, and the examiner's
attention is constantly split between observing the child, checking the administration directions,
scoring ("how many fold is that? OK, four folds, but 2 weren't accurate, and maybe
that beautiful final fold was after the time limit… how do I score that??"),
and keeping time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Because the children enjoy the assessment items, they want to finish their work. I like
children to finish their work too, but the time limits are very short for the children
I work with, and it's very difficult to stop them half way through every single item!
It's not great for rapport or for their sense of accomplishment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I've found it takes more preparation time than other assessments, and it takes longer to score,
compared to something simpler like the &lt;a href="/2015/10/24/dtvp2-vs-dtvp3.html"&gt;DTVP-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It's American. For example, one of the Classroom Observations Checklist items is about
whether the child can carry their tray in the cafeteria. This isn't relevant in most Australian schools.
I've modified this item to be "manages lunch box independently."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tips for Easier M-FUN Administration:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In researching for this post, I've come across a 4 hour e-learning course by Dr Lucy Miller on using the M-FUN-PS.
It's available on the &lt;a href="http://spduniversity.org/"&gt;SPD University website&lt;/a&gt; for US$185, course #2301 and #2302. 
I'm planning to do them soon, so I'll let you know if they're helpful.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It helps to have two people administering the assessment together. I have done it with a physio,
where we took turns between scoring/time-keeping and administering the tasks for the FM and GM sections. 
It's so much easier with two sets of eyes!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep your M-FUN kit ready to go, stocked with everything you need, and make a short
list somewhere (I wrote it in the front of the administration directions book) of the
things you need to gather for each assessment (i.e. fresh crackers, water and napkins for the
Snack Time item, cut out origami templates, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the child wants to take their handiwork with them, make sure you take a photo of it
so you can double-check your scoring if you need to. If possible, video the assessment (or parts)
so you can check things afterwards, particularly the first few times you administer it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I find the M-FUN to be very useful, when a rigorous assessment is
required. It is fun for the child and provides helpful information to the examiner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, there are my thoughts. What are yours? Have you used the M-FUN-PS?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please comment below…&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Bumbo Baby Seat Review</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/12/23/bumbo.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/12/23/bumbo.html</id>
    <published>2015-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2016-03-01T09:48:24+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Use of the Bumbo is a hotly debated topic. Paediatric physiotherapists passionately advise against
it (see MamaOT's post "&lt;a href="http://mamaot.com/beware-the-baby-bumbo-seat/"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Beware the Bumbo&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,"
for example), while many parents claim it is a God-send. As an occupational therapist,
is there a time when I would recommend the Bumbo seat? Short answer: Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But first, what is a Bumbo seat?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://bumbo.com/products/"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Bumbo&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; floor seat is made of low density 
foam with a colourful coating, making it firm but conforming. It is light-weight, 
and comes in one size only (for this specific product). The tray is optional, detachable,
and purchased separately. The premise of the Bumbo is that is keeps the baby safely in a
sitting position, before they have developed the ability to sit unsupported. 
It also keeps baby contained, so they can't roll or crawl away unsupervised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bumbo seat lilac and tray" src="/2015/12/23/bumbo/Bumbo2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="caption"&gt;This is an older style Bumbo, before the strap restraints were
introduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bumbo seats (or "Bumbos") are sold in many baby shops and department stores. In 
Australia, a new Bumbo costs about $70, plus the tray. Since they only fit 
for a short period before baby outgrows it, they are also readily available second-hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This video from Bumbo outlines important safety recommendations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/FdB0vRrtLeg" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why do so many developmental specialists advise against the Bumbo?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MamaOT post, linked above, gives a lovely, detailed explanation. Here is the short version:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When a baby is in a Bumbo, he is trapped. Babies need to move around in order to develop their 
sensory systems, gross motor skills, and fine motor skills. A baby that is restricted too often in
a Bumbo, or in any other containment device, may not develop
as expected, and may be delayed in reaching milestones such as rolling, sitting,
crawling and walking.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Therapists (including myself) are bothered by Bumbo marketing that claims baby can "practice"
sitting up. Sitting in a Bumbo does not help a typically developing baby learn to
sit up. Babies learn to sit up by being on the floor.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Bumbo has had a bad wrap for safety issues. Personally, I feel this is probably
a little sensationalised, and not 100% Bumbo's fault. Most of the injuries to children 
seem to have come by the child trying to escape the seat, or moving around too much, and falling
on their heads by tipping the seat over, or by making it fall from a height. Bumbo have added
a seat belt to try to mitigate the risk, but I really don't like the seat belt. I think the
fault here lies in inappropriate use of the Bumbo.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bumbo with Tray" src="/2015/12/23/bumbo/Bumbo1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The tray clips onto the front of the Bumbo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When I have recommended Bumbo and why:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I agree with points outlined in the MamaOT post - when considering &lt;strong&gt;typically 
developing&lt;/strong&gt; children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, not all children are typically developing. The children I work with
have spina bifida or other similar neurological conditions, which means that for some,
learning to sit unsupported is an unrealistic goal. If we put the rest of their development
on hold until they achieve unsupported sitting, they will not reach their developmental 
potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have recommended the Bumbo for children with lower body paralysis over 6 months 
of age, who need to move on to bimanual (two-handed) play to continue development of
their fine motor skills. Many of the children I work with can sit independently by this
age, but need to prop themselves up with one or two arms. This makes play in a sitting
position very difficult and fatiguing. We recommend corner chairs for this same purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bumbo is always used with a tray (or little table) for
their toys, and we discuss implementation with the family so they understand that the
Bumbo is only to be used for up to 30min at a time, while playing. It's not for watching TV,
or sitting for hours while mum does all the housework. It &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; for banging toys together, 
playing 'ta' games, stacking and nesting, with an adult, for up to 30min.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it's back to the floor…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think? Do Bumbos really need to be taken off the market?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Quick Guide to Mobile Shower Commodes</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/12/09/mobileshowercommodes.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/12/09/mobileshowercommodes.html</id>
    <published>2015-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2016-03-01T09:52:33+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Knowing where to start when prescribing a mobile over-toilet shower commode chair can be difficult.
This quick guide to choosing a mobile shower commode outlines the 10 most important questions that I ask myself
or the user, once it has been established that a mobile shower commode
is required. Choosing the best piece of equipment relies on asking the right questions and 
matching the answers to the most useful features. Before I start asking these questions, I've generally already checked 
that the user's bathroom includes enough circulation space and a level-access shower,
and we've had a discussion about how the mobile shower commode will be used (e.g. 
in the shower, over the toilet, or both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prescription of any equipment always needs to consider the user's preferences, safety, and
sound clinical judgement. The questions I use to guide my reasoning probably won't apply 
directly to your situation, but I thought I'd share this to give my fellow therapists some general information
and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Choosing a mobile shower commode chair" src="/2015/12/09/mobileshowercommodes/mobileshowercommodes1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;With so many options it can be hard to make the right choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These first four questions are really to help narrow down the range of products to
consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Can the user self-propel?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A self-propelling mobile shower commode has big wheels at the 
back (or front), and two small castors at the front (or back). Attendant-propelled 
shower commodes just have four small wheels, so the user is unable to move themselves.
Some manufacturers only provide attendant propelled shower chairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tend to prescribe a self-propelling mobile shower commode
where ever the user is physically and cognitively able to push themselves, and the 
circulation space of the environment allows. This gives the user more freedom and
independence, which is also be important in situation where their safety may be compromised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. What are the user's body proportions like?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer this question, I take a general look at the user, and take some measurements (width and weight) if unsure. 
It's important that the shower commode seat fits well and is comfortable. The user's body and feet need to be well supported.
Standard shower commode seats are generally square, except the bariatric sizes, which are wider than their depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Is the user fairly "standard" in their proportions, so they could fit a standard adult size shower commode (440 x 440mm seat)?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are they a child or very small, so they would best fit a paediatric size (330 x 330mm seat)?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are they smaller than a standard adult, but too big for paediatric, so a Junior size would fit best (400 x 400mm seat)?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are they very big, so they would need a bariatric size (550-900mm seat width)?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are they disproportionate? Would minor modifications, or a custom build be required?
A user with very long legs may require a longer seat depth, and longer leg rests. A user with 
short legs and a short torso may require modified or paediatric leg rests, a shorter seat depth, and a lower backrest height.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. How good is the user's postural control?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider what postural support the user requires in other seats. If they have specialised
seating on their wheelchair, it may need to be replicated on the mobile shower commode.
Some mobile shower commodes (such as the Goanna chair or the Seahorse paediatric shower chair)
include a very supportive moulded seat and backrest, which
is great for those who need it, but can be a barrier to thorough washing and limit independence. If the
user has reasonable balance and postural control, I would steer away from this style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minor postural adjustments can be made to many mobile shower commodes, such as adding 
a lap belt, chest strap, lateral positioning wedges, or a higher backrest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Will the user require "tilt in space"?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some users may have medical conditions that require them to be laid back in a hurry. For others,
tilt in space is required so they can achieve a functional position for using the toilet, a safe transfer,
or for hygiene. While tilt in space is often prescribed on wheelchairs for pressure
relief, this is generally not the case for mobile shower commodes due to the much shorter sitting time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mechanics required for tilt in space add weight and bulk to the chair, not to
mention the extra expense. More moving parts also means more that can break, so
I tend to prescribe tilt in space only when absolutely necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next six questions are directed towards narrowing down on specific features or 
accessories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. How will the user transfer into the mobile shower commode?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three main transfer options:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Standing transfer:&lt;/em&gt; If the user is able to sit into the commode seat from a standing position, swing away leg
rests are usually the best option.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Side transfer:&lt;/em&gt; If the user is transferring sideways from one seat to another, the height of the 
shower commode may need to be adjusted to be closer to the height of the other seat. I have had to lower
shower commode seats in the past because the user was transferring from a wheelchair, which was much lower.
This can be a dangerous game though! If you lower it too much the shower commode won't fit over the toilet!
Check your measurements carefully and allow &lt;strong&gt;at least&lt;/strong&gt; an inch (25mm) clearance. For user who are side transferring,
the location and style of the brakes need to be checked so they are accessible and not interfering with the transfer.
Swing-away arm rests are usually required.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hoist transfer:&lt;/em&gt; If the user is hoisted or lifted into the mobile shower commode, tilt in space may be required. 
The shower commode should also have brakes on every wheel (locking castors). 
It's important to talk through the transfer with the user (and carers if applicable) to make sure the 
equipment will be compatible.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. How often and for what duration will the equipment be used?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the mobile shower commode is used only occasionally, or short-term (e.g. post-surgery), perhaps a 
lighter weight, more simple option would be suitable. Some users need their shower commode for up
to 2 hours every day. In this case, it is important to consider comfort features, such as
padded arm rests, and durability of construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. What seat shape will be needed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some shower commode manufacturers (such as K-Care and Otto Bock) sell seats separately to the mobile shower commode
frame. This allows us to match the seat with the needs of the user. It is important 
to understand and consider all the self-care activities the user needs to perform in the mobile
shower commode. Most shower commode seats are made with a ply wood base, foam top, and 
waterproof vinyl covering. They have an aperture (the hole in the middle), which can
vary in shape, size and location. They can be closed front (first two pictured), open front (third
picture), rear or side opening (less common). The can have a 'bite', a cut-out from the side,
to allow more access without compromising the structural integrity of the seat. The 
&lt;a href="https://www.health.qld.gov.au/qscis/html/equipment.asp"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Queensland Spinal Cord Injury Service&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
has some great templates for measuring and drawing custom-designed seats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mobile shower commode seat options" src="/2015/12/09/mobileshowercommodes/mobileshowercommodes2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Three examples of common mobile shower commode seats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main decisions to make:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Machine-made vs Hand-made:&lt;/em&gt; Machine-made seats (pictured above, centre) are generally much cheaper than 
hand-made, however they often have a heat-welded seam along the inside of the aperture and around the sides of the seat,
which can cause problems for fragile skin. Machine-made seats are often less durable as
the seams can split. Hand-made seats are a must for anyone with sensation-loss, as the 
foam is wrapped from the top through the aperture, so the user's bottom isn't resting
on the wooden base. They are also carefully made with no rough edges. I have never prescribed
a machine-made seat, but they may be appropriate for occasional or short-term users.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Closed front vs Open front:&lt;/em&gt; Open front generally gives better access for washing
and some toileting procedures. Closed front gives better support to the legs, and may 
be required for good positioning. Rear or side opening may be required depending on
the user's bowel management routine.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Size of Aperture:&lt;/em&gt; The default aperture sizes vary according to the manufacturer,
and the size of seat chosen (paediatric/junior/adult). A smaller aperture may be required 
for users who have wasting of their gluts (resulting in bony bottoms), as they may tend to sink too far down through
a large aperture, which is an issue for skin stretching and clearance to roll over the toilet.
Smaller apertures can also assist with maintaining posture.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. What seat padding will be needed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are usually at least two, and often three, standard levels of pressure redistribution
in shower commode seat ranges. The basic level might include a plastic, moulded foam, or machine-made ply and foam seat.
The next level up is generally a hand-made padded seat. The top level is called different things depending on
the manufacturer: "pressure care special", "Dartex" (has extra-stretchy black covering as well as extra foam), 
"JPTR", etc. The top level seats often have dual-layer foam and a stretchy covering. The foam is usually higher.
Keep this difference in mind if you need to specify the seat to floor height.
The vast majority of mobile shower commode users are catered for within this selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those with a very high risk of pressure injury, an extra pressure relief layer can be added, such 
as a gel commode seat topper (available in adult standard size only, closed and open front),
ROHO commode seat cushion (can be made to order), or I've cut a hole in an &lt;a href="http://otequip.info/2015/11/11/equagel-cushion.html"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Equagel cushion&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
which worked quite well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. How will the new piece of equipment fit into the user's lifestyle?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they travel?&lt;/em&gt; If so, a folding shower commode might be required. The ability to adjust the height may
also be useful. Depending on the circumstances, the user might have an ideal mobile 
shower commode for home use, and a more portable alternative for travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do they have to sit for long periods?&lt;/em&gt; Users with neurogenic bowel, such as people with
spina bifida or spinal cord injury, may have to sit for long periods due to their bowel
routine. Sometimes, they may want the option of sitting somewhere other than the bathroom. 
A suitable pan and rack would be needed, and a splash guard. Unfortunately not many 
mobile shower commodes have options for the type of pan/bowl provided, so this may
involve some creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Who else lives in their household?&lt;/em&gt; This may impact on storage options. If the bathroom
is used by others, the mobile shower commode may need to be stored somewhere else.
It's good to have a plan for storage before the equipment arrives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10.  How are the user's needs likely to change over time?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine how the user is likely to change over the next few years, and
go back over all the questions above considering the possible changes. Will your 
original prescription still be valid? I look at getting adjustable features
to manage predictable changes, such as growth in children. With children, we
plan for them to become more independent over time. For someone with a progressive
condition, the ideal shower commode will be easily modified in future with more
support, a higher pressure care seat, or other features they may benefit from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;* * *&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's the end of my "quick" guide to mobile shower commode prescription. They can
be quite straight-forward or a bit tricky to get right, depending on your level
of experience and the complexity of the user. If you're just starting out, it's a 
great idea to get someone to supervise your first few prescriptions, as mistakes can be very costly
and time consuming, not to mention embarrassing! I've been prescribing mobile shower commodes
regularly for 5 years and I still talk through most scripts with a colleague before
submitting them, especially the trickier ones. Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have some mobile shower commode questions or tips - don't be shy.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SmartDrive MX2 Review</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2015/11/26/smartdrivemx2.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2015/11/26/smartdrivemx2.html</id>
    <published>2015-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2016-03-01T09:55:56+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The SmartDrive is a power-assist device that attaches to a manual wheelchair. 
It works by adding a fifth, powered wheel to the rear of the chair. The wheel attachment
also houses the battery, so there is no need for a separate battery pack, as there was
with the original SmartDrive. The SmartDrive's power is controlled by a Bluetooth 
wristband that looks similar to a FitBit, which has an on/off/mode button and a movement sensor
that controls stop/go. Active wheelchair users may appreciate the added boost to their 
functional mobility in the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This video from &lt;a href="http://www.max-mobility.com/smartdrive#mx2"&gt;&lt;u&gt;Max Mobility&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
shows the SmartDrive MX2 in action:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe class="youtube" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8uIXemVXlD4?rel=0" width="853" height="480" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The info I'm providing here has come from a demo session with a supplier, the SmartDrive MX2 User Manual,
internet research, and stories from SBH Queensland therapists (Elizabeth Steele and Angela Tincknell) 
who have used the product with some clients, with varying outcomes.&lt;br /&gt;
If you have more or different information, please share it by commenting below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some specifications:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fitting:&lt;/em&gt; The SmartDrive unit clips into a clamp. Two different size clamps are available 
for fixed frame chairs (standard size fits up to 1in (25mm) diameter camber tube, larger size also available). 
Two different size adaptors are available for folding frame chairs (widths: 11-15in (28-38cm) and 15-19in (38-48cm)).
Only one clamp/bracket is supplied with the SmartDrive, so a choice must be made prior to ordering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Folding frame bracket for SmartDrive MX2" src="/2015/11/26/smartdrivemx2/smartdrivemx2-1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The folding-frame brackets cost about $300 as an upcharge, or more if purchased retrospectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Distance:&lt;/em&gt; Range of up to 20km (12 miles) per charge on fairly flat, easy terrain. Uphill uses more battery power. 
The wrist band should last about 10hrs per charge, and can be turned off when not in use to help it last longer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Weight rating:&lt;/em&gt; 14-150kg (30-331lb) user weight. No comment is made in the manual about whether this includes the
weight of the wheelchair.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unit Weight:&lt;/em&gt; 5.7kg (12.5lb). The brackets and clamps weigh up to 400g.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Charging the Drive Unit:&lt;/em&gt; While in use, the drive unit will beep when the battery depletes to 20% charge, to prompt recharging 
as soon as possible and avoid completely running out. There are 4 blue LEDs on the drive unit that indicate the 
level of charge remaining. To charge the drive unit, it must be plugged into a mains power outlet via the SmartDrive charging 
cable for approximately 3hrs for a full charge. There are 
LEDs on the charge box that indicate power/charging/fully charged. When the drive unit is on, 4 blue lights means fully charged.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Top view of SmartDriveMX2" src="/2015/11/26/smartdrivemx2/smartdrivemx2-2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Power button, charging port and LED configuration&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Charging the Wristband:&lt;/em&gt; When the wristband is in use, a low battery is indicated by the light flashing blue then red every 1.5sec. 
The wristband is charged by USB, so can be plugged into a computer, car charger, or mains power outlet.
A full charge takes approximately 2.5hrs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wristband Details:&lt;/em&gt; The wristband is made from a flexible material, which feels like silicone or a similar polymer. 
The band is fairly easy to don. It involved opening the band, sliding hand through,
squeezing with other hand to slide the two sides of the band across each other, then pushing the stopper through one of the slots.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Wristband at full open setting" src="/2015/11/26/smartdrivemx2/smartdrivemx2-4.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Wristband on maximum open setting&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Travel:&lt;/em&gt; The SmartDrive can be taken on aeroplanes as carry-on luggage. Due to the lithium-ion battery, 
placing the drive unit in checked baggage may not be allowed. 
A certificate can be downloaded from the Max Mobility website to show your airline.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Warranty:&lt;/em&gt; 12 month manufacturers warranty.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Weather and Terrain:&lt;/em&gt; The SmartDrive is mainly intended for indoor and light outdoor use, e.g. shopping in town, 
getting around school/university/workplace, going for a walk down the street, etc. It isn't an "all terrain" option. 
The User Manual outlines conditions to avoid, such as icy surfaces, loose surface (sand, gravel etc.), or standing water 
(puddles or pools). The rep we spoke to advised that small puddles after light rain would probably be OK.
This option wouldn't be suitable for hiking through the bush, using on the farm, or getting down to the beach. It might 
be OK on grass when used in combination with something like the Freewheel.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;em&gt;Cost:&lt;/em&gt; In Australia, approximately $8,500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Use the SmartDrive MX2:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wristband is the main control while using the SmartDrive MX2. It replaces the indoor/outdoor button on the 
original SmartDrive, and makes the unit more responsive. The terminology has also changed
from indoor/outdoor modes to training/everyday modes, though they are pretty much the same thing. The wristband has 
a coloured LED light that indicates the mode:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green = training (indoor) mode, which is very sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blue = everyday (outdoor) mode, which is less sensitive and faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Red = No go, drive unit off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No light = wrist band off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also gives feedback using vibration, but may be inconsistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the user has the SmartDrive attached to their wheelchair, wristband on wrist, and is ready to go, turn the wristband
on by pushing the button. Green mode should be activated. Green mode is
recommended for training beginners, and it would probably be the most appropriate setting for manoeuvring around people and furniture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When outdoors or needing more power, press and hold the button for 5 seconds, until the band vibrates and 
the light turns blue. Now, when the user pushes the wheels, the SmartDrive will maintain the top speed reached. 
The user should let the SmartDrive do all the propelling, but still keep their hands on the push rims for steering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In indoor (green) mode, you can stop the SmartDrive by holding the wheels 
or rims, as per normal manual wheelchair use. &lt;strong&gt;This will not work in 
outdoor mode.&lt;/strong&gt; To stop in outdoor (blue) mode, tap the wrist on the push rims. 
The SmartDrive will turn off, allowing the user to brake as they normally would, 
by holding the push rims. The wristband LED will be red.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the user pushes the wheels again, the SmartDrive will re-engage and return to blue mode. 
This can cause issues in some situations, such as negotiating an obstacle. 
In this case, once stopped, press the button and hold until the wristband is off. 
Turn it on again once after passing the obstacle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Wristband button and LED" src="/2015/11/26/smartdrivemx2/smartdrivemx2-3.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The button requires firm pressure&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SmartDrive MX2 may suit users who:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Live an active lifestyle in a reasonably urban environment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have good wheelchair skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have fast response times, reasonable cognition and sensible judgement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For any user, good training is particularly important. The SmartDrive MX2 isn't a product that can be picked up and used fully from the start.
As there is an extra step required to stop, practice is required before using the SmartDrive MX2 into the community. Conveniently,
a training guide is provided in the back of the User Manual. This is a good start. Clients of therapists I have spoken with have had minor accidents
using this equipment, even once they were familiar with it. For those who do learn to use it successfully, the SmartDrive can take the user's active lifestyle
to the next level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SmartDrive propelling uphill" src="/2015/11/26/smartdrivemx2/SmartDriveMX2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Image from Max Mobility website&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven't prescribed a SmartDrive MX2 yet, but when I do, I will be sure to have at least 1-2hrs 
of client use before prescribing, at least 1 hour set aside for training once they've got it, 
and a week or two of using in very low-risk environments before
taking it into the community. The extent of training required might be a drawback 
for some therapists (unless the supplier is willing and able to provide adequate training)
and the safety aspects may make this product unsuitable for users with slow processing or response times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have any further thoughts or questions about the SmartDrive MX2? 
Please comment - for the benefit of the OT community!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
